<?xml version="1.0"?>
<metadata xml:lang="en">
  <Esri>
    <ArcGISFormat>1.0</ArcGISFormat>
    <SyncOnce>TRUE</SyncOnce>
  </Esri>

  <tool name="ParcelExporter" displayname="Regional Parcel Exporter" toolboxalias="OhioPlanning">

    <summary>
      Bypasses ArcGIS Online export restrictions by connecting directly to the
      GeoOhio Statewide Parcel REST service. No map layers need to be loaded
      into your project. Supports targeted extraction by Statewide, ODOT District,
      MPO Area, County, or a Custom Boundary shapefile or feature class.
      All geometry and attribute data are preserved in a local File Geodatabase.
    </summary>

    <usage>
      1. Open the tool from the Catalog pane (no layers needed in your map).
      2. Choose a Filter Area from the dropdown.
      3. Fill in the sub-parameter that appears for your chosen filter.
      4. Select an Output Folder. A GDB named Ohio_Regional_Export.gdb will be created there.
      5. Click Run.
    </usage>

    <parameters>

      <param name="filter_type" displayname="Filter Area By">
        <dialogexplanation>
          Choose the geographic scale for your extraction.
          "Statewide" downloads all Ohio parcel records (slow — millions of features).
          "ODOT District", "MPO Area", and "County" perform server-side filtering
          so only the records you need are transferred, making them much faster.
          "Specific Boundary" lets you use any polygon layer as a spatial clip boundary.
        </dialogexplanation>
      </param>

      <param name="dist_num" displayname="ODOT District">
        <dialogexplanation>
          Select one of Ohio's 12 ODOT Districts. The tool contains a built-in
          county mapping for each district so no manual lookup is required.
          District 1 = NW Ohio | District 2 = NW (Toledo area) |
          District 3 = N Central | District 4 = NE Ohio (Stark, Summit, Mahoning) |
          District 5 = E Central | District 6 = Central (Columbus/Franklin) |
          District 7 = W Central (Dayton area) | District 8 = SW (Cincinnati) |
          District 9 = S Central | District 10 = SE Ohio |
          District 11 = E Ohio | District 12 = Greater Cleveland
        </dialogexplanation>
      </param>

      <param name="mpo_name" displayname="MPO Name">
        <dialogexplanation>
          Select a Metropolitan Planning Organization from Ohio's 17 designated MPOs.
          The tool maps each MPO to its member counties and downloads only those parcels.
          AMATS = Akron | NOACA = Cleveland | MORPC = Columbus | OKI = Cincinnati |
          MVRPC = Dayton | TMACOG = Toledo | SCATS = Canton | Eastgate = Youngstown |
          LACRPC = Lima | LCATS = Newark | RCRPC = Mansfield | ERPC = Sandusky |
          CCSTCC = Springfield | BHJ = Steubenville | KYOVA = Huntington |
          BOMTS = Wheeling area | WWW = Parkersburg area
        </dialogexplanation>
      </param>

      <param name="county_name" displayname="County Name">
        <dialogexplanation>
          Select any of Ohio's 88 counties from the dropdown list.
          County-level extraction is the fastest single-area download option.
          Supported counties: Adams, Allen, Ashland, Ashtabula, Athens, Auglaize,
          Belmont, Brown, Butler, Carroll, Champaign, Clark, Clermont, Clinton,
          Columbiana, Coshocton, Crawford, Cuyahoga, Darke, Defiance, Delaware,
          Erie, Fairfield, Fayette, Franklin, Fulton, Gallia, Geauga, Greene,
          Guernsey, Hamilton, Hancock, Hardin, Harrison, Henry, Highland, Hocking,
          Holmes, Huron, Jackson, Jefferson, Knox, Lake, Lawrence, Licking, Logan,
          Lorain, Lucas, Madison, Mahoning, Marion, Medina, Meigs, Mercer, Miami,
          Monroe, Montgomery, Morgan, Morrow, Muskingum, Noble, Ottawa, Paulding,
          Perry, Pickaway, Pike, Portage, Preble, Putnam, Richland, Ross, Sandusky,
          Scioto, Seneca, Shelby, Stark, Summit, Trumbull, Tuscarawas, Union,
          Van Wert, Vinton, Warren, Washington, Wayne, Williams, Wood, Wyandot.
        </dialogexplanation>
      </param>

      <param name="boundary_feat" displayname="Custom Boundary Feature">
        <dialogexplanation>
          Browse to a polygon layer (shapefile or feature class) that defines
          your study area — for example a township boundary, a buffer zone, or
          a custom planning area. The tool will spatially intersect the statewide
          parcel service against this boundary and export only the records that
          fall within or touch it. The boundary layer must be visible in your
          current ArcGIS Pro project.
        </dialogexplanation>
      </param>

      <param name="out_folder" displayname="Output Folder">
        <dialogexplanation>
          Select the destination folder for your results. A File Geodatabase
          named "Ohio_Regional_Export.gdb" will be created here automatically.
          The exported feature class will be named Parcels_{FilterType} inside
          that GDB. Using a local drive (C: or D:) rather than a network path
          will give the fastest write speeds for large datasets.
        </dialogexplanation>
      </param>

    </parameters>

  </tool>
</metadata>
